A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Counselor's Office, Records, 2001-2009 (bulk 2006-2009)
Library of Virginia
- IV. Attorney General Settlements, 2006., Extent: 0.70 cubic feet (2 boxes). (Box 17-18)
  - 2006 (part five) (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - 2006 (part six) (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - 2006 (part seven) (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - 2006 (part eight) (Box 18, Folder 3)
- V. Files of Lawrence Roberts, Counselor to the Governor, and Shane Emmett, Legal Fellow, 2004, 2006-2009., Extent: 5.25 cubic feet (15 boxes). (Box 19-33)
  The Files of Lawrence Roberts, Counselor to the Governor, and Shane Emmett, Legal Fellow series is housed in 15 boxes. The provenance of this series is unclear; most of the records appear to be from Roberts. However, the records were received from Emmett in January 2010. This series contains clemency petitions from prisoners submitted to the Governor. The clemency petitions usually include: petition from prisoner, constituent letters (for and against clemency), court documents and opinions, summary of the case provided by the Office of the Attorney General, and a memorandum to Governor Kaine from Counselor to the Governor (Lawrence Roberts, 2006-2009) and/or Shane Emmett, Legal Fellow, providing background information on the case, analysis of petition and conclusion/recommendation to Governor. Files are arranged chronologically (by date of execution, clemency, or stay of execution). This series also includes a few conditional pardon applications, and records related to the Jens Soering case and right-to-life license plate. This series contains confidential, privacy-protected and attorney-client privileged records and is closed for 75 years per Code of Virginia, 2.2-3705.1, 2.2-3800 and 42.1-78.
  Clemency petitions and/or correspondence were submitted on behalf of: Dexter Lee Vinson (executed 27 April 2006); Brandon Hedrick (executed 20 July 2006); Michael Lenz (executed 27 July 2006); John Yancey Schmitt (executed 9 November 2006); Kevin Green (executed 27 May 2008); Percy Levar Walton (death sentence commuted to life in prison without parole, 9 June 2008); Robert Yarbrough (executed 25 June 2008); Kent Jackson (executed 10 July 2008); Christopher Scott Emmett (executed 24 July 2008); Edward Nathaniel Bell (executed 19 February 2009); John Powell (scheduled 14 July 2009 executed stayed by United States Supreme Court, executed on 12 March 2010); Norfolk Four (conditional pardon granted on 6 August 2009); John Allen Muhammad (executed 11 November 2009); and Larry Bill Elliott (executed 17 November 2009).
  Notable documents include: memo to Governor Kaine from Delacey Skinner, Communication Director, 20 April 2006, discussing the drafting of Kaine's first clemency statement in the case Dexter Lee Vinson (Kaine opposed the death penalty but pledged to carry out death sentences) (b19, f1).
  Notable documents in the Brandon Hedrick file include: memorandum to Governor Kaine from Roberts, dated 17 July 2006 on Hedrick's clemency request (b19, f2); annotated petition (probably by Roberts) for clemency on behalf of Hedrick, undated, submitted by Robert Lee and James Broccoletti (b19, f2); and handwritten letter to Kaine from Hedrick, dated 7 June 2006, asking Kaine to commute his sentence to life in prison and declaring his innocence (b19, f3).
  Notable documents in the Michael Lenz file include: two versions of a memorandum to Governor Kaine from Roberts, dated 24 July 2006 on Lenz's clemency request (b19, f4); and annotated petition (probably by Roberts) for clemency on behalf of Lenz, 11 July 2006, submitted by Matthew L. Engle and Jennifer L. Givens (b19, f4).
  Notable documents in the John Yancey Schmitt file include: letter to Governor Kaine from Bill Beachy, Schmitt's step-father, dated 10 November 2006, describing the final meeting between Schmitt and his mother, Carol Beachy (b20, f1); memorandum to Governor Kaine from Roberts, dated 2 November 2006, providing background of case and making cases both for and against clemency (b20, f1); Roberts' notes from 27 October 2006 meeting with Schmitt's attorneys (b20, f1); Roberts' notes from 25 October 2006 meeting with Schmitt's mother, Carol Beachy (b20, f1); and highlighted clemency petition on behalf of John Yancey Schmitt, 19 October 2006 (b20, f2).
  Notable documents in the Kevin Green file include: memorandum to Governor Kaine from Roberts, dated 22 May 2008, on Green's clemency petition (b20, f5); Roberts' notes from 20 May 2008 meeting with Green's attorneys (b20, f5); and highlighted clemency petition on behalf of Kevin Green, 15 May 2008 (b20, f5).
  Percy Levar Walton killed three innocent people over a two-week period in November 1996 and was sentenced to death. A few days before his scheduled execution date of 28 May 2003, the United States District Court for the Western District of Virginia granted Walton a stay of execution in order to determine Walton's mental competence. In July 2003, the court ruled that Walton was competent to be executed. A three-judge panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit vacated the lower court ruling, directing a broader inquiry into Walton's mental state. Before that inquiry took place, the entire U.S Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit reconsidered the panel's decision in an en banc review. On 9 March 2006, the court found Walton competent to be executed by a narrow 7-6 majority. Walton's attorneys submitted a clemency petition to Governor Kaine on 22 May 2006, presenting evidence that Walton had schizophrenia and that his mental state had deteriorated since 2003. Kaine delayed Walton's June 2006 execution date until 8 December 2006 for the purpose of conducting an independent evaluation of Walton's mental condition and competence. After a six month review, Kaine concluded that Walton was serious mentally impaired and that he met the United States Supreme Court's definition of mental incompetence. Kaine acknowledged that Walton's mental impairment was not permanent and delayed the execution by 18 months, to 10 June 2008. Walton's condition did not improve during that time and on 9 June 2008 Kaine commuted his sentence to life in prison without parole.
  Notable documents in the Walton file include: Marion Correctional Treatment Center, Admission Psychological Evaluation of Walton, dated 9 September 2008, and Greensville Correctional Center, Psychological Evaluation of Walton, dated 3 July 2008, both records provided to Roberts by Secretary of Public Safety John Marshall (b22, f1); memorandum to Governor Kaine from Roberts, dated 28 November 2006, following up on Kaine's June 2006 reprieve; the memo describes the arrangements made for Dr. Mark J. Mills and Dr. Anand Pandurangi to interview and evaluate Walton; Mills interviewed Walton on 10 November 2006; Pandurangi interviewed Walton on 22 November 2006; both interviews were conducted at an interview room at Sussex Prison and were recorded by a hidden video camera (b22, f1); digital video cassette tape, DVD copy, and 2 audio CDs of Dr. Mills' 10 November interview of Walton at Sussex Prison; 2 digital video cassette tapes, DVD copy and 2 audio CDs of Dr. Pandurangi's 22 November 2006 interview of Walton at Sussex Prison (b22, f2); 18 October 2006 meeting notes on procedures for evaluating Walton; attending: Larry Roberts, Walter "Mac" McFarlane, Gene Johnson, Dept. of Corrections Director, Robin Hubert, Dept. of Corrections Medical Staff, Secretary John Marshall and Deputy Secretary Clyde Cristman (b22, f3); memorandums to Governor Kaine from Roberts on establishing independent procedures to evaluate Walton, 2 October 2006 and 27 September 2006 (b22, f3); notes from 31 August 2006 conference call between Roberts and Mac McFarlane and John Howley, Jennifer Patterson and Arthur Brown, Walton's attorneys (b22, f3); memorandum to Governor Kaine from Roberts, dated 3 June 2006, on Walton's clemency request (b22, f3); e-mail to Roberts from Walter "Mac" McFarlane, Virginia Dept. of Correctional Education, dated 31 May 2006, describing McFarlane's thoughts on the Walton clemency petition (b22, f3); application for clemency on behalf of Walton, 23 May 2006 (b22, f4); documents in support of clemency petition (b22, f5-b23, f4); and copies evaluations of Walton by Dr. Mark J. Mills, Ruben C. Gur, Ph.D., Dr. Alan J. Arikian, Dr. Miller M. Ryans, Dr. Patricia General, Allen Glasgow, Stanton Samenow, Ph.D., and Dr. Anand K. Pandurangi (b23, f5-b24, f2).
  Notable documents in the Robert Yarbrough file include: memorandum to Governor Kaine from Roberts, dated 23 June 2008, on Yarbrough's clemency petition (b24, f3).
  Notable documents in the Kent Jackson file include: memorandum to Governor Kaine from Roberts, dated 9 July 2008, on Jackson's clemency petition (b25, f1); and notes from 7 July 2008 meeting between Roberts and McFarlane and Andy Protogyrou and Colston Jones, Jackson's attorneys (b25, f1).
  Christopher Scott Emmett was convicted of murdering his friend and co-worker John Fenton Langley on 10 October 2001. Emmett was sentenced to death and was scheduled to be executed on 13 June 2007. Emmett filed a writ of certiorari with the United States Supreme Court seeking review of his conviction, as well as a motion to stay his execution. The Court denied his stay motion, with four Justices voting to grant his stay. However, the Count had yet to consider Emmett's writ of certiorari and would not considered it until September 2007. Governor Kaine granted a stay of execution until 17 October 2007 in order for Court to consider Emmett's writ. The Court denied the writ on 1 October 2007. Emmett's lawyers petitioned the courts, and filed a supplemental petition with Governor Kaine, challenging the constitutionality of lethal injection as a method of execution. On 17 October 2007, the United States Supreme granted a stay of execution while it reviewed the issue. The Court upheld the constitutionality of lethal injection as a method of execution in the Court's 16 April 2008 Baze v. Rees case. The Court lifted Emmett's stay of execution in May 2008. Emmett was executed on 24 July 2008.
  Notable documents in the Emmett file include: Robert's notes from telephone call with Matthew Engle, Emmett's attorney, dated 15 October 2007 (b25, f5); Roberts' notes from 9 October 2007 meeting with the Office of the Attorney General (b26, f2); Roberts' notes from 6 June 2007 meeting with Matthew Engle, Emmett's attorney (b26, f5); and memorandum to Roberts from Shane Emmett, dated 29 May 2007, on Emmett's clemency petition (b26, f5).
  Notable documents in the Edward Nathaniel Bell file include: memorandum to Governor Kaine from Roberts, dated 6 February 2009, on Bell's clemency petition (b27, f3); and letter to Roberts from Kelly Timbrook, widow of Sgt. Ricky Timbrook, Bell's victim, dated 5 January 2009, imploring Kaine not to commute Bell's sentence (b27, f3).
  Notable documents in the Paul Warner Powell file include: memorandum to Governor Kaine from Mark Rubin and Shane Emmett, dated 8 July 2009, on Powell's clemency petition (b27, f5).
  The Norfolk Four refers to the men (Derek Tice, Daniel Williams, Joseph J. Dick, Jr., and Eric C. Williams) convicted in the rape and murder of Michelle Moore-Bosko in 1997 in Norfolk, Virginia. The Norfolk Four alleged their confessions were coerced by threats from law enforcement that if they didn't confess they would receive the death penalty. Wilson served his full 8 and a half year sentence. On 6 August 2009 Governor Kaine granted a conditional pardon to Tice, Williams and Dick; the convictions remained on their record but the men were released from prison.
  Notable documents in the Norfolk Four file include: notes from meetings between attorneys for the Norfolk Four and Counselor to the Governor (b28, f2 and f5); memorandum to Governor Kaine (probably from Roberts), ca. 11 May 2009, on the impact of the Norfolk Four on the clemency process (b28, f2); memorandum to (either Governor Kaine or Roberts) from Helen F. Faye, Chair of the Virginia Parole Board, dated 8 May 2009, on the Norfolk Four clemency petition (b28, f2); briefing binder to Governor Kaine and Roberts from Shane Emmett, dated 19 December 2008, containing documents regarding the Norfolk Four clemency petition (b28, f3-f4); memorandum to Roberts from D.J. Hansen Commonwealth's Attorney, City of Chesapeake, dated 5 March 2009, rebutting allegations in the Norfolk Four clemency petition and book "The Wrong Guys" (b28, f5); e-mail to Shane Emmett from Helen Fahey, dated 21 April 2009, express her views on the Norfolk Four case (b28, f5); and memorandum to Carrie Henderson, Deputy Scheduler, from Roberts, dated 25 January 2008, on Norfolk Four meeting with Governor Kaine (b29, f1).
  John Allen Muhammad, the "Beltway Sniper", was convicted of the murder of Dean Meyers on 17 November 2003 and was sentenced to death. Mohammad was executed on 11 November 2009. Notable documents include: memorandum to Governor Kaine and Mark Rubin from Shane Emmett, dated 2 November 2009, providing factual background, clemency petition summary and analysis (b29, f2); petition for executive clemency for John Muhammad submitted in video format, submitted 15 October 2009 (b29, f3); and memorandum to Rubin and Emmett from Dave Roberts, Legal Fellow, dated 18 October 2009, on standards for the insanity defense and commutation of death penalty sentences for allegedly insane offenders (b29, f3).
  Notable documents in the Larry Bill Elliott file include: memorandum to Governor Kaine and Rubin from Emmett, dated 6 November 2009, providing factual background, clemency petition summary and analysis (b29, f4); memorandum to Rubin from Katherine Burnett, Senior Assistant Attorney General, dated 11 September 2009, providing her perspective on several aspects of Elliott's clemency petition (b29, f5); letter to Kaine from Elliott, dated 31 August 2009 (b30, f1); and clemency petition on behalf of Elliott, 28 August 2009 (b30, f1-5).
  Larry Fowlkes, convicted in 1995 of murder and sentenced to 45 years in prison, filed a clemency petition to Governor Mark Warner in 2004 asking for his release based on his claim of innocence and on medical grounds. Warner did not act on the petition prior to leaving office in January 2006. Fowlkes' attorneys submitted an additional petition to Governor Kaine in July 2006. Fowlkes died in prison in May 2008 without Kaine acting upon his petition. Notable documents include: original petition submitted to Governor Warner in December 2004 and supplemental petition submitted to Governor Kaine in July 2006 (b31-b32, f3).
  - Dexter Lee Vinson, executed 27 April 2006 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Brandon Hedrick, executed 20 July 2006 (part one) (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Brandon Hedrick, executed 20 July 2006 (part two) (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Michael Lenz, executed 27 July 2006 (part one) (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Michael Lenz, executed 27 July 2006 (part two) (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Michael Lenz, executed 27 July 2006 (part three) (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Michael Lenz, executed 27 July 2006 (part four) (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - John Yancey Schmitt, executed 9 November 2006 (part one) (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - John Yancey Schmitt, executed 9 November 2006 (part two) (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - John Yancey Schmitt, executed 9 November 2006 (part three) (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Kevin Green, executed 27 May 2008 (part one) (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Kevin Green, executed 27 May 2008 (part two) (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Kevin Green, executed 27 May 2008 (part three) (2 volumes) (Box 21)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 and 2008 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part one) (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part two) (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part three) (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part four) (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part five) (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part six) (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part seven) (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part eight) (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part nine) (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part ten) (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part eleven) (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part twelve) (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part thirteen) (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Percy Levar Walton, 2006 [commuted to life without parole, 9 June 2008] (part fourteen) (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Robert Stacy Yarbrough, executed 25 June 2008 (part one) (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Robert Stacy Yarbrough, executed 25 June 2008 (part two) (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Robert Stacy Yarbrough, executed 25 June 2008 (part three) (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Robert Stacy Yarbrough, executed 25 June 2008 (part four) (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Kent Jermaine Jackson, executed 10 July 2008 (part one) (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Kent Jermaine Jackson, executed 10 July 2008 (part two) (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Kent Jermaine Jackson, executed 10 July 2008 (part three) (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Christopher Scott Emmett, executed 24 July 2008 (part one) (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Christopher Scott Emmett, executed 24 July 2008 (part two) (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Christopher Scott Emmett, executed 24 July 2008 (part three) (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Christopher Scott Emmett, executed 24 July 2008 (part four) (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Christopher Scott Emmett, executed 24 July 2008 (part five) (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Christopher Scott Emmett, executed 24 July 2008 (part six) (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Christopher Scott Emmett, executed 24 July 2008 (part seven) (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Christopher Scott Emmett, executed 24 July 2008 (part eight) (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Christopher Scott Emmett, executed 24 July 2008 (part nine) (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Christopher Scott Emmett, executed 24 July 2008 (part ten) (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Edward Nathaniel Bell, executed 19 February 2009 (part one) (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Edward Nathaniel Bell, executed 19 February 2009 (part two) (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Paul Warner Powell, death sentenced stayed by U.S. Supreme Court on 13 July 2009 [executed 12 March 2010] (part one) (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Paul Warner Powell, death sentenced stayed by U.S. Supreme Court on 13 July 2009 [executed 12 March 2010] (part two) (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Paul Warner Powell, death sentenced stayed by U.S. Supreme Court on 13 July 2009 [executed 12 March 2010] (part three) (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Norfolk Four, conditional pardon granted 6 August 2009 (part one) (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Norfolk Four, conditional pardon granted 6 August 2009 (part two) (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Norfolk Four, conditional pardon granted 6 August 2009 (part three) (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Norfolk Four, conditional pardon granted 6 August 2009 (part four) (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Norfolk Four, conditional pardon granted 6 August 2009 (part five) (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Norfolk Four, conditional pardon granted 6 August 2009 (part six) (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - John Allen Muhammad, executed 11 November 2009 (part one) (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - John Allen Muhammad, executed 11 November 2009 (part two) (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Larry Bill Elliott, executed 17 November 2009 (part one) (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Larry Bill Elliott, executed 17 November 2009 (part two) (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Larry Bill Elliott, executed 17 November 2009 (part three) (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Larry Bill Elliott, executed 17 November 2009 (part four) (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Larry Bill Elliott, executed 17 November 2009 (part five) (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Larry Bill Elliott, executed 17 November 2009 (part six) (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Larry Bill Elliott, executed 17 November 2009 (part seven) (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Larry Bill Elliott, executed 17 November 2009 (part eight) (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Richard Michael Wolfe case, correspondence to Governor Kaine from Terri Steinberg (Wolfe's mother), 2007 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Tahliek Taliaferro case, notes from 10 June 2009 meeting between Office of the Counselor to the Governor and Undie Brown, Kaa Caputo (Taliaferro's mother), and Wayne (mother's boyfriend) (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Larry Fowlkes, 2004 (part one) (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Larry Fowlkes, 2004 (part two) (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Larry Fowlkes, 2004 (part three) (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Larry Fowlkes, 2004 (part four) (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Larry Fowlkes, 2004 (part five) (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Larry Fowlkes, 2004 (part six) (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Larry Fowlkes, 2004 (part seven) (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Larry Fowlkes, 2006 and 2008 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence re: Joseph Dick and Davey J. Reedy, 2006 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Jackie Everette Rife, Conditional Pardon, 22 November 2006 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Mario A. Bustillo, Conditional Pardon file, 2006-2007 and 2009 (part one) (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Mario A. Bustillo, Conditional Pardon file, 2006-2007 and 2009 (part two) (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - John Thomas Bailey Harrison III, Conditional Pardon request, 2009 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Subject Files
    - Jens Soering petition, 2008 (part one) (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Jens Soering petition, 2008 (part two) (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - James Monroe Memorial Foundation, 2009 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Caroline County, 2008 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Virginia State Board of Elections/Virginia Office for Protection and Advocacy, 2006 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - SB 817: Constitutional Analysis of the "Choose Life" license plate legislation, 2009 (part one) (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - SB 817: Constitutional Analysis of the "Choose Life" license plate legislation, 2009 (part two) (Box 33, Folder 7)